[Music]
hey everyone
this is part of a series of films that
rebel wisdom is putting out about the
crisis in sense-making
because i think the problem of truth the
collapse of institutional authority
and how we come to truth together is
right at the core of all of the other
problems that we're seeing
i'd recommend you start with part one
which kind of outlined the
the situation as i see it this is a talk
that i gave to a university in america
lafayette college
i almost called it the intellectual dart
web is dead i kind of wish that i had
and i think it's it's essential history
to understand where we're at now
that we're going to build on over the
next
few weeks
[Music]
i started working for channel 4 news and
the bbc
yeah just over 10 years ago now 2000
and rebel wisdom goes back about 18
months something like that
back in 2017 i went out to
i know jordan peterson has talked here a
while ago and i went out to
to canada actually just to go watch one
of his lectures and thought well i might
as well get an interview with him while
i'm out there i'm a journalist so i
applied got an interview you came in
from where
i came in from london i ended up making
the first documentary about him i
got the interview and then thought well
no one's actually kind of done a
documentary about his thoughts i put
that together
and then just after i put that out
literally about three or four days after
i put that out
he went on channel 4 news and had that
very famous viral interview with kathy
newman
that maybe some of you might have seen
and i used to work with kathy newman
so i was actually in the office in
channel 4 news
probably about two weeks maybe a month
before that interview went out so i was
still freelancing there while i was a
while i was doing documentaries and so i
was like this is a
really weird position to be in i put out
the first documentary about jordan
peterson
and then he kind of rockets to fame on
the news program that i used to work for
so i was like what am i supposed to do
with this and the irony was a lot of
what i talked to him about was
synchronicity
this kind of jungian psychological idea
of
coincidences that have a deeper meaning
so i was like this is
kind of a weird synchronicity what am i
supposed to do
so for a while i started trying to
negotiate behind the scenes between
kathy newman and jordan about
maybe doing another interview because i
don't know if you remember after the
interview there's a lot of controversy
and
jordan felt that um the channel four was
sort of spinning that kathy was the
victim and
there was a lot of stuff going on on
twitter and it was kind of like watching
two people that i
knew and knew were good people and
trying to sort of
bring them back together to have a
dialogue and
jordan was really keen and kathy wasn't
so i was like okay that's not going to
work
so in the end i put together this film
called glitch in the matrix
looking at the kathy newman interview
and why it had gone viral and what it
said
about the media sort of the balance
between the mainstream media the
alternative media
what it said about us as a culture and
it became so jordan put it onto his
channel it's now got about
two and a half million views on his
channel in that film i
i put in a few criticisms of channel
four news and
a few criticisms of kathy newman so i
knew when i put that out that
i was making it much more difficult like
to go back into the newsroom and
i kind of knew that i was kind of ending
my career with in the mainstream media
by doing it
but i just had this sense that there was
something more exciting kind of on the
other side
and rebel wisdom pretty much started
through that that piece
but this is why the the topic of the
intellectual dark web
is quite close to my heart because i
feel that there's some skin in the game
then like i kind of
put all of my chips on jordan peterson
and the intellectual dark web
and so when that that first glitch in
the matrix film
was out or when i was putting that out
literally in the last week or so that i
was working on it
i saw this thing called the intellectual
dark web on the dave rubin show and i
thought that's a quite
interesting concept i put a few lines in
the film and then put it into the title
so literally about two weeks after the
idw was named
fortunately thanks to youtube podcasting
and however else you get shows like this
one
the mainstream media strangle hold on
information
which really is a stranglehold on your
ability to think clearly
about the issues of the day is crumbling
at an incredible rate
now the question is who and what will
replace it
a few months ago one of my favorite
people to sit across this table from
eric weinstein came up with the phrase
intellectual dark web to describe this
eclectic mix of people from sam harris
to ben shapiro to his brother brett
weinstein to jordan peterson
all of whom are figuring out ways to
have the important and often dangerous
conversations that are completely
ignored
by the mainstream this this next clip is
a set of
um little pieces from jordan peterson
heather heing and a few other people
who've been in our films
it's like a herd of cats right
because so i've thought about well what
what
what unites us to the degree that
there's an us because that's not so
self-evident
there's enough of an us so that the name
emerged and it's stuck
so so there's something in common
because otherwise the name
wouldn't have stuck right you can't name
nothing
it doesn't work so what is the
intellectual dark web
people in the group tend to reject
orthodoxy tend to reject ideology
tend to be interested in first
principles thinking
meaning that if you you don't take
something
on faith it's a very smart
concept to try to corral a very
difficult group of very disparate people
into one orbit i would say
it is actually the manifestation of the
process of thinking
that's more important than the
conclusions that are generated you need
a group of people who are willing to say
hey you know you made a better point
i've changed my mind
and i've learned something that i didn't
think about and
that kind of integrity in a conversation
is what characterizes a lot of the
internal idw discussion to me it's that
people agree
not on their positions they may not even
agree as to what the facts are but they
usually agree as to what constitutes a
conversation
so yeah the idw was kind of a coming to
consciousness
of a conversation that been growing
organically online for quite a while
and then when it when it sort of
surfaced it caught on because a lot of
people recognized it
as a kind of emergent phenomenon and
one of the people on our channel daniel
thorson talked about
peterson in particular jordan peterson
in particular breaking a conversational
seal which i thought was a really
beautiful way of looking at it
in this talk i'd like to to talk about
kind of what the initial idea of the idw
was
and whether it's it's kind of lived up
to its promise
lived up to its ideals and lived up to
the kind of initial pitch
and i think it it both has and hasn't
it's certainly very very successful i
mean
i'm part of about four or five different
facebook groups set off off the back of
the idw
and it certainly worked as a meme like
it took off i think jordan peterson's
framing of
it the name stuck and it certainly
refers to something
and that sort of question of what it
refers to i think is really at the
center of this
kind of point because it's it's often
seen is it is it a meme
is it a particular group of people is it
a way of conversing there's all of these
different ideas and i think all of them
have some
truth and i'd like to kind of go through
some of those different
uh ways of looking at it and also talk
about
what i think it represents and i think
one of those
is this sort of alternative media
ecosystem it was kind of a coming to
consciousness of an alternative media
ecosystem
the kind of official coming out of the
idw was this new york times article that
came out
in over a year ago so barry weiss is a
opinion uh writer with the new york
times and she wrote this piece
that was was kind of the the lightning
rod
it had already existed so sam harris had
talked about it i think
eric weinstein i talked about it dave
rubin had talked about it and this was
the new york times kind of giving it his
blessing a little bit
and so the official kind of start in
terms of
mainstream media was was about this time
there was a paradox of it kind of
shifting because as soon as it was
acknowledged by the mainstream media it
was no longer dark
and so there's a kind of paradox and it
was criticized at the beginning
people were saying how can you say that
um joe rogan who's probably the most
powerful
broadcaster around is in this dark web
this is ridiculous
so and that that's kind of true a lot of
the people in there are some of the most
popular and most
successful podcasters and media
personalities like douglas murray in the
uk as the
editor of the spectator or the
associated editor of the spectator the
oldest magazine
so there's a kind of paradox i'll read
out the names of all of the people who
were in that
first new york times article so sam
harris eric weinstein dave rubin brett
weinstein heather heing
jordan peterson ben shapiro douglas
murray
maggie noires iron hersey alley
christina hoff summers
joe rogan claire layman and deborah soh
um they and
this is interesting because eric
weinstein is
was the key so there were pictures of
about i don't know
maybe 10 altogether of the people who
are in there and these all very sort of
heavily stylized pictures like there's
there's sort of a
it was a deliberate sort of um i don't
know what would you say almost a
mystique around it from the beginning
um and it's interesting as well that
eric is the first person featured
because eric is probably is nowhere near
as well known as say dave rubin or
joe rogan but that's quite significant i
think there was a few sort of central
thoughts that the idw centered around as
as we heard already in some of those
clips the idea that there are certain
things that can and can't be said in the
mainstream media
that long-form content allows for
the exploration of ideas that the
mainstream media is now sort of
putting into like 30-second sound bites
if you're lucky and
and that just encourages polarization it
encourages
um oppositional thinking and maybe we
can start to kind of have much more
nuanced discussions
um but also it's formed around the idea
that there are certain ideas that are
so nuanced and so difficult to discuss
takes of gender as an example like
and that's the obviously the cathy
newman jordan peterson discussion that
if you force it into a kind of
mainstream media
perspective you just you can't do it it
needs longer to explain
and a nuanced perspective to be to be
held
and and also but there's a much deeper
story to the idw as well that i think we
explored quite well in the second film
so we did glitch in the matrix one and
then we did glitch in the matrix two
that was who's seen that has anyone seen
that you're nodding have you seen it
no you've seen it um so glitch in the
matrix two was really eric weinstein
talking about
why he thought the the idw was necessary
where it came from and he has a a story
that goes back
to the 1980s and he i
and i believe him i believe his story i
think he's i think he he's
he's on to something so eric weinstein
is a mathematician
physicist and gave a talk
to oxford in i think 2009 where he he's
got a a theory called geometric
unity that he thinks could be a theory
of everything
so this is the kind of level that he
kind of is looking at the world and
thinking
about the world on and his theory is
that looking at the institutions
since the 1980s what we've done in the
west
is created institutions that have kept
out heterodox thinkers
where like the fresh ideas usually come
from the marginal figures
the difficult figures the ones who won't
go along with the consensus
and that we've created um structures
that basically push those people out
and that's what for him the idw is it's
sort of the
that's within the media it's all the
people who've been pushed out and all
the perspectives have been pushed out of
the media
but his theory about the idw goes all
the way
down to that's why we haven't had the
advance in physics that's why biology is
stuck
this is something that brett talks about
like biology has been stuck
since the 1960s eric says like string
theory is a completely wrong
turn it's unverifiable all of these
different areas have become stuck at the
same time because of this sort of
central idea that we've pushed out all
the heterodox thinkers
and we've done it because we don't
understand that these difficult
characters
of of which eric is definitely one um
and
a lot of a lot of his a lot of his story
a lot of the
the the story and glitch in the matrix
too is based around his experience as
well why he
why he felt that his ideas weren't being
respected weren't being
um taken in and and why all of these
institutions have got stuck at the same
time
it's kind of the the the idw is this
sort of
the the public face
of a conversation that needs to happen
within the lots of these institutions
that have been captured by groupthink
captured by consensus so that's another
sort of deeper layer to it um
because sometimes on on the films that
we put out we get comments on youtube
saying
this was just a kind of this was just a
one-off conversation this was just
eric was just throwing something out
you're reading too much into this it's
like well
maybe but eric's possibly reading too
much into it as well um
and i'm also convinced that um
again i don't know this i've obviously
spoken a fair bit to some of these
people behind the scenes but i don't
know this
from those conversations i'm pretty sure
that
eric's a very persuasive guy and i'm
pretty sure that he's persuaded a lot of
the other members of the idw
this is the this is what the overall
perspective is
and so it's kind of an existential
threat from that perspective like there
is a kind of
um yeah there's a very powerful
narrative underneath a lot of this
so this talk is really that the central
question for me is
whether the idw is is still creating
novelty it's
still creating newness because it i
sense that it was
at the beginning of um when i first
became aware of it mostly on the rubin
report you had
conversations between sam harris no
sorry between
ben shapiro and jordan peterson that
seemed to be going into new territory
you had
conversations between brett and eric
that seemed to be going into new
territory and there's a sort of
aliveness
to the conversations that i've not seen
so much of recently
and i wonder why that is i've got a few
ideas um
i also want to say that what i'm saying
now i'd love this to start a
conversation
i know that we're kind of doing this for
um for youtube as well
these are my ideas like this isn't the
final word on it i'm i'm sort of putting
out some ideas but this is just sort of
starting a conversation about
why this might be the case if it's true
that it's not creating as much novelty
as it did
so again sort of coming back to what is
the idw
is it this group of people or is it a
way of interacting one of my favorite
perspectives is from um a guy called
ryan bennett
who was central to the idw
meetup in new york after
a conference there failed to happen he
he sort of took so he's quite he's quite
connected with a lot of the people
in the idw and i really like this so his
concept is
he's a he's a computer programmer and he
says
trying to make sense of the idw by
looking at who's in it is like trying to
make
sense of the internet by looking at
what's on your hard drives
so the i try and see it as a kind of
network protocol
so a network how do you understand the
internet well you understand how the
computers are talking to each other what
the ip
protocols are that tells you a lot more
about what the internet is
than the the contents of what's on it
um and i like i like this as a as a
concept
um when you pursue truth instead of
power you're in the idw and you favor
understanding over judgment
value ideas more than identity you're in
the idw again
i think it's really worth thinking about
these as ideals and asking kind of how
much
the the conversations in the idw have
have
lived up to these ideals um
yeah i'd like to play the clip number
five this is
this is brett and eric on the ruben
report this for me is one of the most
compelling
framings of what the conversation of the
idw
should talk about and the territory it
should cover
and once we give up on the idea that
anybody
on the map today has the answer with
respect to the policies that we are
supposed to embrace once we say actually
everybody's policies are a failure if we
were to enact
uh the libertarian program it would fail
for
game theoretic reasons if we were to
enact the socialist program
it would fail for game theoretically
same thing right so the point is okay
fresh sheet of paper with respect to
policy now there's a lot for us to talk
about
starting from values you can say we
don't actually have the answer we don't
know it's very important that the people
who are certain
be silent because they are not the
important people at this moment
yeah i find that quite a um compelling
framing
and taking yeah just sort of saying that
that we need a new form of conversation
with a new a new set of starting points
um i want to go back to who is in the
the idw because there's a lot of people
who are who are
being framed as being part of it and i
think one of the
one of the a good place to start is with
uh stephen pinker
said everyone know who stephen pinker is
um
so i'll just recap very quick very
quickly he's a is he at harvard
uh yeah yeah and he's a team
yeah and he what's his official um
linguistics
professor of linguistics psychology and
holistics perhaps
yeah cool so stephen pinker famously
is a famous big head
academic who keeps
writing the same book about how the
world's getting better and better and
better and how everything is wonderful
and we just should be be grateful for
the miraculous times that we live in
um and he's also spoken out about some
of the same topics that
members of the idw talk about kind of
the ideological capture of the
universities and some of those big
topics
and he's often linked him with the idw
and it's i think it's a really
interesting
it's very illustrative about what the
idw is to say
why i don't think he is and i think that
that most of the idw core would probably
not think that he was as well at least
from the way that they explained the idw
um and that's because and this is a real
tension within
within the sort of core of the idw as
well because i see it most cleanly and
sort of jordan peterson but
this are we living in the the best of
times or are we living in a world that
is kind of
degrading fast and we're in an
existential crisis
and i hear jordan peterson sometimes
speak to one side of that and sometimes
speak to the other
but stephen pinker is clearly on that
side of things eric
and brett and i'd say sam harris as well
and maybe some of the other members of
the idw are very much on the other side
and
if you watch glitch in the matrix 2 the
film with with
with eric he frames it very much as a
kind of existential crisis and we need
to
create spaces where we can speak freely
because of this existential crisis
so i think that that for me takes the
idw
as it was originally conceived out of
the realm of just
kind of anti-like pro pro free speech
movement it's more than that as it's
originally kind of conceived
and so now i'm going to move on to
kind of given the pitch for what the idw
is meant to achieve and
and now i'd like to talk a little bit
about what some of the criticisms are
and
what i consider um valid criticisms of
the idw
and the first i'd love to play that clip
from and this is very
prophetic in a way because this is again
eric and brett talking on the rubin
report
and i'm going to come back to dave rubin
quite a bit later on because
he's such a central figure in the idw
kind of
framed very much as the home of the idw
and also host of many of the original
conversations
and i think he's so identified with it
that the
flaws in his um
the way he conducts himself and now kind
of reflecting on a lot of other
a lot the idw in general but this i
think is one of the really key
points of the dangers of of this kind of
movement maybe there's a missing piece
here which is
our economic system when you plug it
into certain things
very directly like journalism i think
actually this is your point of view
that is truth-seeking which cannot
withstand direct contact with market
forces
that when you do that you generate um
artificially feeble truth-seeking
mechanisms
and it eventually invades them all so
how hard is it to beat the mainstream
news outlets
not very hard because they're so bad at
delivering very hearted analysis
it's very hard to beat them at some kind
of competition right
competitively they're extremely dominant
but in terms of what they're trying to
deliver
they're terrible um likewise the
university system
yeah because i think
initially the way that the idw was
framed was that
because they're not part of a corporate
structure because they are they have
their own podcasts they
have independent audience and their
independent means they can be they can
avoid that sort of capture by market
forces and corporate forces
but that's just not that's just not the
case i mean i know
from running a youtube channel you're
constantly aware of
what the commenters are saying on your
your channel and you get to kind of you
feel that as a kind of
gravitational force you know what they
like you know what they don't like
you've started monetizing it so you know
what the the paying fans want and what
they don't
and so it's absolutely the case that
um if you're starting up a podcast
or if you're starting up your own media
channel you're not immune from those
forces at all
and you're not immune from um so market
forces you can kind of look at kind of
financial forces but you can also look
at it like
sex power and all those other social
dynamics are also market forces what
you're doing for
kind of rep for reputation and
that starts to kind of interfere with
searching for truth as well
just just the fact that there is a
comment thread and knowing what the
audience
like and what they don't like you can i
mean if you you'd have to not be human
to not
to not feel that in some way yeah yeah
yeah i feel it too and i think we should
be honest about that and be able to
laugh at it a little bit
and i think to sort of zoom out a little
bit of you know you and i have talked a
lot before
and i keep coming back to this line of
the danger the dangers that lurk in
something like the idw conversation
or even followers and fans of it is you
know
once this mistake that i've come to to
notice or basically
profess is that there seems to be a
trend of people
who think the moment that they have
rejected bad philosophy or a bad
philosophy it also means they've
rejected bad psychology
and they really have nothing to do with
each other it doesn't mean
you're not susceptible to the lores of
status and sex and money
and all of these other things and even
some if someone rejects a political
leaning being like oh i've noticed that
the left is really wacky and has gone
overboard and look like i'm
i woke to this in sort of the red pill
way or either side of that if
whatever your political epiphany is that
doesn't mean you've escaped the normal
trappings that we all deal with of weak
psychology and and they they relate but
they don't they don't
they don't correlate the way that i
think a lot of people tend to
to jump the gun and think they have and
that goes for the personalities in the
idw that goes for the big names that we
all know who are on stage that goes for
people like you and i who are trying to
sort of tell the story of these people
it goes for people following it
i think we all have to just sort of be
honest about that again laugh about it a
little bit it's
if there's anything that binds us as
humans together that would be a great
thing to sort of
you know find common ground
even with your political enemies like
we're all susceptible to these kind of
things
we should admit that and then what you
do with it is
is really important also once you
once you identify yourself as they did
with
the idw being a thing you start to
create aligned intense
incentives like they're they're talking
uh speaking tours together or book deals
or all of that sort of stuff that starts
to come in
and then especially on something like
twitter where you're kind of like
is innately tribalizing you're then
sticking up for each other and those
kind of factors
so you start to create a tribe around an
anti-tribal
um ideology you it sort of becomes a
little bit paradoxical
and and i think that paradox has been
playing out quite a bit um
and talk a little bit about like one of
the things i think the idw
at its best or the members of the idw at
their best
do is create a sort of high resolution
critique of um
culture like cultural movements gender
is a perfect example that i've talked
about before
like those conversations have to be had
with real nuance and real
real delicacy and they're very easily as
soon as they come down to a lower level
a low resolution perspective and i think
you're it's almost like a lie
um the high resolution perspective is
very illuminating the low resolution one
is just a cliche
and i think at their best some of the
people in the idw do hold that
that um high resolution critique
but at their worst i think they do uh
slip to a low resolution critique
um like jordan peterson at his best is
very high resolution at his worst he
kind of
it comes down to very sort of it can be
quite simplistic kind of reacting
against the excesses of the left and
it just becomes quite kind of cliched um
dave rubin who's highly identified with
the idw
like his his whole thing is like how the
left has gone insane
and that's pretty much the whole frame
that he that he puts everything through
and i think that's that's not searching
after truth
i mean if you're going to search after
truth i think you need to have a more
high resolution critique than that also
this sense of tribalism
is kind of going against tribalism has
it created new tribalism i think we've
got
the piece here that kathy young wrote
for collette
um where she she looked at what is the
unifying
factor behind the people who are seen as
being part of the idw
and it's often been called reactionary
um and i i know that
people in the idw wouldn't like that
phrase but i think there is some truth
in it i think they are reacting to
something
and the question is whether it's
something that needs to be reacted to
like how widespread is
the ideological capture of um
institutions now and how dangerous is
that
and the biggest criticism of the idw i
think and kathy points to that in this
piece is
that they are becoming tribalists
themselves just there are these
these huge forces that pull you towards
tribalization especially on social media
and
um particularly on twitter where most of
this conflict is
is happening so so a lot of the
commentary on the idw is kind of asking
okay what is the thing that unites the
people within it
and i mean obviously part of that is
going to be sort of a resistance to
extreme kind of ideological uh thinking
on the left what you might call kind of
woke culture
and there's a question of what that
actually means and whether that is the
new dividing line in culture
yuri harris had a few articles in
colette around that
and eric weinstein has kind of agreed
with that and he says that the main
dividing line is this
upgrade to the left if you break
progressivism or the left or whatever
you want to call it
into the traditional liberal core
of the left and then uh you augment that
with a
fairly recent extremely aggressive
upgrade
which appears willing to attack
reason civility as agents of oppression
you know are tools of oppression
um i think that that
upgrade is really what is it an issue
and a question
what is it what is being questioned
and if you believe that upgrade that
extremely post-modern
um adjustment to classically
progressive positions if you think that
is now the new dominant
left and it's not going away you
probably take a fairly dismissive
attitude towards the entire left of
center
cannon of thought and i would say that
there are members of the
of the idw who believe
that uh this current aggressive strain
has displaced classically liberal or
classically progressive positions
which will never return and that we now
need to deal with the fact that that
upgrade
is permanent and those people have
probably
um decided that they are going to
abandon any hope
in a left-of-center position well i held
that position that that upgrade if you
will
that marginal difference um in a level
of aggression
and willingness to attack reason and
data and evidence
and itself in favor of tying people in
not
logically and epistemologically um if i
thought that was permanent
i would understand exactly why people
were completely abandoning
any kind of high-resolution view of the
now it happens that i understand why
they're saying that but i disagree i
believe that many people are fairly
moderate and liberal in their views
and are going through a period akin to
the mccarthy era which i've called left
carthyism
in which it's very dangerous to simply
say the obvious which is when you're
attacking
reason or one of two genders or
concepts as abstract as patriarchy or
anything like that
you probably made a fairly significant
wrong turn somewhere
um in your thinking so this is another
another frame i find particularly useful
to understand kind of the culture
war dynamic at the moment a friend of
mine peter lindbergh wrote this piece a
white paper
about culture war 2.0 saying if culture
war
1.0 was about left versus right what we
actually have
now is a kind of fragmentation of the
culture war
where we have maybe i don't know exactly
how many maybe 12
different what he called mimetic tribes
fighting each other
and he did a spreadsheet with all of
their memetic tribes like what they
believe and how
a lot of the the real fighting that
we're seeing at the moment is kind of
in the left like between different
tribes on the left or between different
tribes on the right
and he yeah really worth checking this
on out maybe we can send you some of the
links after
after the talk um and in this he also
talked about the value
of what he called mimetic mediation
which is like how do you mediate between
the different warring tribes
and i think that's a really really
valuable concept that i'd like to see
kind of
being spread a bit more because that
that's another criticism of the idw that
i think is worth making
is i don't see them reaching out so much
to people in other tribes
and looking at kind of negotiating
between them if
i don't see much strategy in having
people from
different tribes onto their shows for
example in dialoguing with them i see
them mostly commenting and talking to
people
within their particular tribe um
and then there's often kind of defenses
where people talk about bad
faith you can't talk to that person
they're a bad faith actor
i would i would probably i'd suggest
that
um yeah memetic mediation is something
finding someone who is in one of the
tribes but is able to
able to dialogue so i think people right
in the center of those tribes are
probably unreachable but there's always
people on the outside who are
open to dialogue and open to to
communication
and i don't see that happening so often
the other criticism of the idw
i would say is the need to embrace
criticism
and there's a there's a dialogue between
eric weinstein and sam harris saying
that they're both getting worse
they feel that they're getting worse
because most of the criticism that
they've had so far has been really
low quality and that they need better
better quality criticism
yeah and the other point is that the idw
was very
specifically framed as an environment a
group of people who would come together
discuss things and potentially change
minds
and i genuinely can't think of a single
example
where someone in the idw has changed
their mind over
anything significant over what the last
18 months or so since the idw came along
and if the idw is a project that
is able to kind of carve out a beachhead
and then potentially
create an a space in culture for people
to cha have conversations and change
their minds
if they're not even doing that within
the idw itself how on earth they're
going to
do that or model that for everyone else
in
to eric's point probably about what what
you
want in sort of in any system you want
a method of error detection and
correction david deutsch is my favorite
thinker i think i tweet about him more
than anyone else i'm a huge fan of david
deutsch's work and he sort of pins
that um sentence as may if there's a
commandment of the universe that you
could try to derive from the universe
itself and the famous is off distinction
it would be something like that
that sustaining
and building the systems to detect and
correct errors of course you have to
decide what an
error is and that's a different
philosophical question is the most
important thing and for that
eric's right for thinkers you what you
want is an incubator that can detect and
correct errors
um and if it becomes tribal and it has
biases that start building within it
that it that there's certain errors that
just
are never detected maybe i'm pointing to
some of the errors of like
you know pretending that we're animals
that suddenly don't want sex because
we're sitting in an idw
room or something like that you want you
want an ability to detect and correct
errors
and open discussion and a culture of
criticism
is um is important to uphold so in that
respect
tribal thinking if it becomes um
if it becomes unable to to
correct itself is is i would say
an objective wrong and an objective evil
in the universe to sort of
borrow some more deutsche language and
and central to that i think
is is dave rubin because dave reuben has
been
center who here knows who does everyone
here know who dave reuben is
reuben report um
so i've got a little clip um so a little
clip of the interview that i did with
with dave
um in the summer i think
um yeah yeah well i guess if there's a
physical center
of the intellectual dark web it's right
here i mean it's in my garage because i
think this
is where not where the ideas all started
but at least where most of the
connections between the people started
and you know people ask me my role in
this whole thing and
whether it is a thing at all you know
whether it is some sort of card carrying
organization or it's this loose
affiliation or whatever
it is uh i think my role in it is i've
been a little bit of the
connective tissue between the people and
the criticism i've seen is that you
don't push back hard enough against
people
when they maybe deserve it that you give
an easy ride to people
listen i would say i'm interviewing
people the way i like to interview them
i like to sit across from somebody look
them in the eye
and figure out what their ideas are the
bigger you get the more relevant you get
the more haters are going to come out
but the more that legitimate criticism
will come out too and again
i address this all the time what do you
think is the most legitimate criticism
it's not really for me to say what the
legitimate criticism of me
if someone wants to say that they don't
like the way i interview or that i don't
ask hard enough questions or something
like that
well i suppose that is a legitimate
criticism of me
it's not the way i like doing my
business and you know if you don't like
what i'm doing then i would say you
don't have to watch
i wanted to interview him and i've been
wanting to interview him for a while
after seeing those first reuben report
uh
shows and but when i started researching
and the
in the run-up to it and i was just
looking at some of his old old programs
i was thinking out there's something a
little bit
off here and it's not just
so reuben famously interviews
controversial figures
and that's fine i think that's a
valuable thing to do but
only if you're giving the audience the
necessary information to make up their
own minds about who these people are
ask them push them about certain things
that they've said
so in the in the research for it and
then
subsequently there's an amazing series
of films by a guy called timber on toast
called dave rubin's battle of ideas
which is a fantastic watch it's
literally four hours
of forensic analysis of what the reuben
report does and how it does it
that is really an amazing piece of work
a running theme which i want to be
constantly shining a spotlight on
throughout this whole thing
is exploring how well the reuben report
does in achieving its
main goal of fostering open and honest
conversations
about ideas yeah timber it's really good
to catch up
i really enjoyed your your films and it
looked like you put an awful lot of work
into making them
why did you go to so much work like four
hours
just based on the ruben report the main
reason was
um i could see that there was a lot of
criticism emerging online but that
people would rarely
provide substantive examples of the
things that they were accusing dave
of um and i think when you've got that
criticism without examples or without
like justification
it does come across as quite sort of
malicious
and it doesn't seem like it's it's like
good faith
um so my main motivation in making the
videos was
so i knew the examples because i
followed dave for a long time
from the beginning of his show like
2015. um
i'd been there for all the kind of
example interviews as the ad that come
up the ones that i sort of pointed out
and i thought if i assemble these in a
tight structure that people can easily
follow people who
have watched them and people who have
never watched him then
at least when these criticism come up
people can look into them
and know what they're based on if after
watching my videos
they have no problem still with the
interview style or the way he conducts
things
that's fine uh but at least then they
that they know
what it's based on so so how would you
summarize
those criticisms so i'd say firstly that
he never pushes back on guess therefore
whenever there is an idea presented that
needs to be investigated
into like its strengths and weaknesses
the audience
aren't given a chance to explore that
because they don't see the counter
argument or the challenge
and the other criticism would be that he
sanitizes and savory characters
um not by platforming them which i think
is the straw man kind of argument of
what it is i think he sanitizes them by
presenting them as something they are
not
whenever there's a chance to get to the
bottom of some sort of
controversial thing they've said in the
past he skirts around it
or does something to obfuscate it i
think those are the two main criticisms
you almost have to go to that level to
really sort of to see what's being done
um but but generally he'll have stefan
molyneux or
tommy robinson who's a famous kind of um
sort of street fighting politician from
the uk katie hopkins is a
provocateur journalist this guy tommy
sotomayor
who is sort of famous for being quite
anti-semitic
and he he doesn't ask them those kind of
questions doesn't doesn't put their
words to them
if dave's interviews expose that people
at the forefront of his struggle against
the authoritarian left were xenophobic
or misogynistic or white supremacists or
rape apologists
it would deprecate the viewers
perception of the show's value
and their connection to its emotional
core dave therefore has to carefully
sidestep around his guests
asking softball questions helping them
to deliver blows against their opponents
and flattering them at every step of the
journey to ensure that they are shown
in the best possible light the dishonest
framing of guests which we see in
episodes of the ruben report
isn't a glitch it's a feature
a key selling point discussing
controversial topics
is all well and good but it's worth very
little if you don't combine it with
debate
and challenging questions to put the
guests on the spot and get to the root
of their ideologies
that would take actual courage
intellectual curiosity and rigor
and it's definitely not an easy thing to
do you know it might mean that your
guests refuse to do your show again
it might mean that they stop inviting
you along to do talks alongside them on
stage
and it might mean that all those
invitations you're getting to speak for
right wing groups conveniently dry up
but maybe that's what would need to
happen in order for you to deliver the
honest
worthwhile exchange of ideas which you
keep telling us that your show is all
about
as a journalist i felt i had to push him
on that and had to ask him those
questions
um and what i've seen since is
that he refuses to engage with with
people who criticize him or
ask questions about the show i've seen
him do that a lot on twitter
and he claims that no one he claims that
left wingers don't want to go on the
show
he has all of these right wingers on the
show because they want to come on and
the left wingers don't want to come on
hey dave um so i've been watching your
program since about like early time in
high school now i'm in college so
it's been a while but um one thing that
i really liked
something that you talked about here was
the difference between a
diversity of thought and diversity of
identity
sure now the thing with a diversity of
thought is i feel like that's a problem
you actually perpetuate on your show
because the only time you really have
left-wing guests are when they're
members of the intellectual dark web
such as harris or weinstein and they're
only there for the bulk of the time
to uh talk about the regressive left and
so i
pretty much wanted to ask you why won't
you have sam or sam cedar on
yeah he's recording it too okay yeah i
mean the guy's just he's just a
dishonest player who's just lied about
being repeatedly like
i'm not gonna do it so would you be
willing to have natalie wynn of contra
point or david pakman or kyle kalinski
all of these are progressives who have
i'm not in principle i'm not against
having any of them but i'm not gonna
have people that attacked me personally
i think it's pretty obvious if you watch
what i did up here
like i don't attack people personally
i'm happy to talk about ideas
you're gonna go after me personally if
you're gonna lie about me and slander me
and things like that like
it's just not the game i'm playing
there's no win in it you know i have a
certain set of rules when it comes to
talking to people and how i sort of
behave as a public person
so he wasn't very happy with the
interview i did um
had very little contact with him
afterwards and then it kind of shut down
completely and i've heard now that
that has happened to a lot of other
people who've tried to raise any any
concerns
with him and i i think it's worth
highlighting this because i think it
illustrates quite a lot about the
dangers of the idw this sort of
slipping down to a tribal perspective
and
also i i genuinely think that this he's
obviously not the only person that does
this but i think he's probably the most
high profile person who does
what i see him doing on twitter is
framing anyone who criticizes them as
being back
motivated by bad faith or kind of a bad
person
basically a quillette which is run by
clara lehmann who's a former guest of
mine who has been very
friendly and nice to me uh on my show
and
in all of our private exchanges has done
about four hit pieces on me recently
where they're really trying to single me
out out of the idw crew
that i'm somehow the worst because i sit
down and and talk to some people that
they don't like and i
talk to these people on the right and i
don't question them exactly as they want
and all of these things
and they keep just writing piece after
piece now i got a ton of haters
these days
which really is just the sign that i'm
doing something good i mean it really is
and then the good liberals are just
freaking out right now and that's also
why they're coming down on me
because i've left and i've survived and
you got to extract a pretty heavy price
on a guy like that because if you look
at my resume if there's a
back of a baseball card and you look at
my numbers you'd be like no this guy has
to be with them
yeah but i'm not and because of that
they're like what we can't just let him
walk we gotta break his knees
you need to go and support him and be
part of what he's doing because he's
under the gun now
okay understand this he's being attacked
by some of the most vitriolic and
dangerous people on earth and if you
guys do not support him now
then you're part of the problem it's
it's the it's akin to you guys
sitting on the side and watching your
neighbors be slaughtered
because they haven't come to your house
yet this is the last message i probably
have for
where i think the idw can go wrong or
what i think it needs to do is just to
actually embrace criticism
embrace criticism have the critics on
the shows have some
maybe have some even kind of heated
discussions if needed and what i see
them doing far too often is
is only talking to the people who
already agree with them about most of
the central stuff
i'm gonna i'm gonna slip in a slight
curveball here and i don't know
how this is gonna land um this is uh ken
wilber
who um brandon has been getting into
quite a bit recently
okay so ken wilber is a philosopher he
created something called integral theory
in about the 90s so it had a real
high point in the 90s and early 2000s al
gore was a real fan of
integral theory so there's a kind of
sliding doors moment
with the florida election was if al gore
had become
become president we might be living in a
very different world now if it wasn't
george bush
but but ken wilber has this
theory about how consciousness evolves
that i think is really really useful as
a frame
to see where the idw
sometimes slips into a very simplistic
narrative and when it sometimes goes
beyond that
so this is a little graphic that i made
to go at the beginning of a film that i
did with ken wilbur i think it's useful
jordan peterson has become a global
celebrity by weaving together
mythology science philosophy
and religion into a compelling theory of
everything
one of the most influential philosophers
of the last decades
did something similar ken wilber
is the creator of integral theory
another attempt to pull together much of
the world's knowledge
and spiritual traditions into a theory
of everything
integral theory gained a big following
in the 90s and 2000s
and remains influential after serious
health problems over the last decade
ken wilbur is now returning to the
conversation
what do these two hugely influential
thinkers have in common
where do they disagree and what can they
learn from each other
a lot of times when it comes to jordan
peterson it's not that i'll disagree
with much of what he says i i
agree with much of what he says it's
some of the things that he leaves out
i find this a little bit interesting
because he's clearly an integral thinker
to get the most out of this film
we'll need to introduce a little
integral terminology
at the core of integral theory is the
idea that cultures and societies go
through specific levels of development
in the same way as individuals do
becoming more sophisticated as they
develop
or grow up it's an idea that's common to
developmental theorists
including peterson's favorite jean
piaget
you move from one knowledge structure to
the next one which includes the previous
one
and is better and it's better because it
covers more territory
that's how you know it's better it does
the same thing the old tool does
plus some additional things so it's a
definition of better
integral theory represents this
development as a spiral
in this film we'll mostly be talking
about amber
tribalism ethnocentric authoritarian
which first emerged about five thousand
years ago
orange modern values the rational self
that emerged 300 years ago with the
liberal democracies
and the beginning of universal values
green the values of relativism multiple
perspectives
dialogue and consensus human rights
sometimes called postmodern which
emerged fully
in the 1960s they're healthily
integrated
they support each other but each of them
can believe that their way of looking at
the world is the only true way
and then they are mutually exclusive
for wilbur the incomprehension between
these world views
is what's causing many of the worst
excesses of the culture wars
above these levels wilbur says is
another level
called integral or second tier
from this perspective it's clear that
each of the previous ways of seeing the
world has value
and needs to be integrated um
so i don't know if this is really
confusing or helpful but
basically the idea is
so ken wilber's map and i've met a few
people who talk about this as
an integral os like an integral
operating system
is very very helpful to understand
especially
with what happened when so green post
modern was
uh civil rights feminism the the idea
that before then you had
orange values which was basically
there's one way of looking at the world
it's based on science it's based on kind
of
um it's based on a sort of single
perspective and then
what we had coming in in the 60s and and
developing after it was the idea that
there are multiple perspectives that are
not being included
and that's that's an advance that
that realization is actually an advance
on the previous one because there are
perspectives that are not included there
are
voices that are not being heard bringing
those in is really essential
but what can happen and what's been
happening
um over the last 10 15 years
by wilbur's um uh
perspective is that if you if you forget
that or what you can end up with is just
a cacophony of voices like you lose the
idea of truth altogether like true ever
all truth is relative so you've just
lost the idea of any kind of central
truth
you've lost the eye all truths just
become perspectives
and then what you end up in is kind of
narcissism and nicholas
and if that's where we are and i think
that there's some truth to that
um that the theory is that these these
these levels of development
um they they emerge and then they become
pathological just before we move on to a
new level of development
um so i think from this perspective
what the idw is generally doing is
pointing out most of the flaws with
green with postmodern with saying
there is a truth um it's not just about
perspective
and the danger is that
i think at its worst the people in the
idw don't see that that is actually
a positive value that it is valuable to
see different perspectives
and the idea with integral the teal one
at the top
is that it's its second tier
is considered um an evolution of
consciousness where you can actually
start to see that all of these different
levels before have some value and that's
where i think
at its best the thinkers on um
the intellectual dark web and i'd
include someone like jonathan height
here as well
he he's very good at seeing that
most of our political beliefs are
temperamental
so thinking that someone's kind of worse
or better based on their political
beliefs is like you're judging someone
for the way that they're wired rather
than
uh just their for for what they think
so there's a there's an e-book that um
ken wilber wrote around this called
trump and a post-truth world i would
really highly recommend if anyone's
interested to know know more about this
this frame and my sort of final thought
is
that eric in glitch in the matrix ii
and in his sort of framing of the the
idea of the idw was saying that
it's needed to because of the corrupting
effect of group think and aligned
incentives within institutions
and the kind of paradox is that by
creating the idw i think they've
actually made themselves subject to some
of those same forces
and and that's a kind of paradox of in
the naming and creation of it
it sort of has allowed it to be captured
by some of those same forces
so thank you very much for for listening
we're going to have a
few questions in a q a now
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching and see you soon